<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ben's Development Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bdarnell.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bdarnell.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-13T10:10:58-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://bdarnell.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ben Darnell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cross-Python development with auto2to3]]></title>
    <link href="http://bdarnell.github.com/blog/2012/03/13/cross-python-development-with-auto2to3/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-13T09:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://bdarnell.github.com/blog/2012/03/13/cross-python-development-with-auto2to3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>2to3</code> can be a useful tool for developing Python libraries that work
with both Python 2 and 3, but it&#8217;s fallen out of fashion because it
intrudes into the development process in awkward ways and generally
slows things down.  In spite of its weaknesses, I believe <code>2to3</code> is
a good approach for many libraries to support multiple versions of
Python, so in this post I&#8217;ll share the approach and tools I used
to add Python 3 support to <a href="http://www.tornadoweb.org">Tornado</a></p>

<h2><code>2to3</code> vs single-source</h2>

<p>The major alternative to <code>2to3</code> is to use a single source tree written
to the common subset of all supported versions of Python.  This is a
viable approach even for large projects, as shown by e.g.
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/django-developers/XjrX3FIPT-U">Vinay Sajip&#8217;s work with Django</a>.  However, the resulting code
requires many <a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/wiki/PortingNotesFor2To3">compatibility shims</a>, and looks
somewhat unnatural from the perspective of both Python 2 and 3.  This
is especially true if compatibility with Python 2.5 is desired &#8211; many
features that ease the transition to Python 3 were introduced in
version 2.6.  Personally, I prefer the workflow afforded by <code>2to3</code>, in
which the source code remains more-or-less normal Python 2, but it
works on Python 3 as well.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Getting started</h2>

<p>You&#8217;ll need a good unit/regression test suite to ensure that things are
working as expected in Python 3.  In addition, your package should be
installable with a standard <code>setup.py</code> command.  Finally, of course,
check your third-party dependencies to ensure they are compatible with
Python 3.</p>

<p>You&#8217;ll need the following tools:</p>

<ul>
<li>At least one build of Python 3.  Since the early versions of Python 3
saw relatively little adoption, it&#8217;s generally safe to skip 3.0 and 3.1
and go straight to 3.2.  On Ubuntu you can install multiple Python packages
from the <a href="https://launchpad.net/~fkrull/+archive/deadsnakes">deadsnakes ppa</a>; on a Mac try Homebrew or Macports.</li>
<li><code>2to3</code>: Included in recent versions of Python (as far back as 2.6,
although we&#8217;ll be using the version in 3.2)</li>
<li><code>virtualenv</code> and <code>pip</code>:  The de facto standards for managing multiple
Python environments.</li>
<li><code>distribute</code>: The Python 3 successor of <code>setuptools</code>, necessary for
running <code>2to3</code> automatically at install time.  <code>virtualenv</code> will
install this automatically, so there&#8217;s no need to download it separately.</li>
<li><a href="http://tox.readthedocs.org/en/latest/index.html">tox</a>: A virtualenv manager and test runner.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bdarnell/auto2to3">auto2to3</a>: My own contribution to the Python 3 toolchain, <code>auto2to3</code>
makes it easier and faster to work with <code>2to3</code>.  Note that <code>auto2to3</code>
must be installed in a Python 3 environment; the other tools on this
list will generally be installed under Python 2.</li>
</ul>


<p>Setup procedure:</p>

<pre><code>virtualenv -p python2.7 ~/envs/py27
virtualenv -p python3.2 ~/envs/py32
~/envs/py27/bin/pip install tox
~/envs/py32/bin/pip install auto2to3
</code></pre>

<h2>Iterating with <code>auto2to3</code></h2>

<p><code>auto2to3</code> is an import hook that automatically runs <code>2to3</code> on demand.
The converted file is cached on disk so subsequent runs are faster.
Its command-line interface is similar to that of the Python
interpreter; it accepts both filenames and module names (with <code>-m</code>) to
specify the program to run.</p>

<p>For example, to run the Tornado test suite under both Python 2 and 3, do:</p>

<pre><code>~/envs/py27/bin/python -m tornado.test.runtests
~/envs/py32/bin/python -m auto2to3 -m tornado.test.runtests
</code></pre>

<p>At this point, if you&#8217;re lucky, you&#8217;ll see a long list of failures (if you&#8217;re
unlucky, some failure happened early enough that it prevented the rest of the
test suite from running).  Errors you&#8217;re likely to encounter include:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Bytes and unicode don&#8217;t mix&#8230;</strong> The big change in Python 3 is that
there is no longer an implicit conversion between byte strings and
unicode strings.  Attempts to use one when the other is expected will
usually result in <code>TypeErrors</code>.  Bugs of this type are often (but
not necessarily) bugs in Python 2 as well, but would only manifest when
non-ascii characters are used.</li>
<li><p><strong>&#8230;Except when they do.</strong>  There&#8217;s an implicit conversion between bytes
and <code>str</code>, because <code>str()</code> can convert any type to string.  This is
an indirect conversion via <code>repr()</code>, and is unlikely to be what you want:</p>

<pre><code>  $ python2.7 -c 'print str(b"foo")'
  foo
  $ python3.2 -c 'print(str(b"foo"))'
  b'foo'
</code></pre></li>
<li><p><strong><code>2to3</code> gets some things wrong.</strong> For example, it assumes that
calls to <code>.keys()</code> refer to the <code>dict</code> method (which changed to an
iterator in Python 3) and wraps them in <code>list()</code>.  More esoteric issues
include some problems with the three-argument form of the <code>raise</code>
statement.  When you see these kinds of errors you may need to rework
the code to run correctly both with and without <code>2to3</code>, or in some cases
disable the relevant <code>2to3</code> fixer.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>As an example, <a href="https://github.com/facebook/tornado/commit/3b3534c2436326328620fbea2626a30ea5e79f13">this commit</a> (with 316 lines
changed) is the one that merged most of the Python&nbsp;3-related
changes to the Tornado master branch.</p>

<h2>Wrapping it up</h2>

<p>Once your tests are passing with <code>2to3</code>, it&#8217;s time to prepare the package for
distribution.  In <code>setup.py</code>, do something like this:</p>

<pre><code>import sys
import distutils.core

kwargs = {}
if sys.version_info[0] &gt;= 3:
    import setuptools  # setuptools (aka distribute) is required for use_2to3
    kwargs["use_2to3"] = True

distutils.core.setup(
    ...
    **kwargs)
</code></pre>

<p>This will run <code>2to3</code> automatically at installation time, so everything should
just work for people installing your package under Python 3.</p>

<p>Once the initial port to Python 3 is done, it&#8217;s often more convenient
to treat Python 3 just like any other Python version.  This can be
done by running tests under <code>tox</code> before each commit.  It&#8217;s slower
than <code>auto2to3</code> since it doesn&#8217;t cache the converted output, but it&#8217;s
a more realistic simulation of real-world installations.  Create a
file <code>tox.ini</code> (in the same directory as <code>setup.py</code>) that looks
something like this:</p>

<pre><code>[tox]
envlist = py27, py32

[testenv]
# Change these variables as needed.
commands = python -m tornado.test.runtests
deps = pycurl

# python will import relative to the current working directory by default,
# so cd into the tox working directory to avoid picking up the working
# copy of the files (especially important for 2to3).
changedir = {toxworkdir}
</code></pre>

<p>Now run <code>~/envs/py27/bin/tox</code> and it will run your tests under both Python
2.7 and 3.2.</p>

<p>Once you&#8217;ve tested everything enough to be confident in a new release,
just upload a new build to PyPI and it will be installable via
<code>pip</code> in both 2 and 3.</p>

<h2>The future</h2>

<p>Once the initial work of porting is done, I&#8217;ve found it to be fairly
simple to maintain compatibility as development continues - I work
mainly in Python 2.7, and test the other versions via <code>tox</code>.  The most
common error that is caught in my Python 3 test runs is forgetting to
mark the ascii string literals I use in unit tests as byte strings,
which is easily remedied.</p>

<p><code>2to3</code> is of course a transitional tool, and at some point you&#8217;ll want to
switch to working mainly in Python 3.  It should be possible to adapt
this workflow to go in the other direction with <code>3to2</code>, but I haven&#8217;t
pursued this approach yet mainly due to the lack of standardized support
for running <code>3to2</code> automatically in <code>setuptools</code>/<code>distribute</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
